Guide to the King County Labor Council Records
Special Collections, University of Washington Libraries
King County Labor Council records
1889-2012
University of Washington Libraries Special Collections Box 352900 Seattle, WA 98195-2900
1940
AFL-CIO.$bKing County Labor Council of Washington
53.94 cubic feet 73 boxes
Coordinating and decision-making body of the various union locals in King County, Washington
The King County Labor Council has long been the communal decision-making body of the various union locals in King County. From the mid-1920s until the reunification of the AFL and CIO in 1955, only AFL-affiliated unions were represented on the Council. At other times, however, the vast majority of King County's locals had a voice on the Council.
The Council has passed through at least four distinct periods in its history. The Council originally began in 1888 as the Western Central Labor Union. This body changed its name to the Central Labor Council of Seattle and Vicinity in 1905. These groups occasionally joined coalitions with Populists and other reform groups in local and state politics. Nonetheless, much of the early Council's energy was spent simply trying to survive. The second phase of the Council's history began roughly in 1914 with the labor shortage that allowed unions to organize much of Seattle. The Council grew increasingly radical in this period and became the dominant force in Seattle's powerful progressive coalition. The loss of the Council's power began with the mass layoffs of shipyard workers after World War I. These layoffs led the Council to call the Seattle General Strike of 1919, the only truly city-wide general strike in American history. Employers responded to the failed strike with an open shop drive that de-unionized most of King County. A series of internal power struggles plagued the Council after the strike. The Council voted to expel members of the Industrial Workers of the World in late 1919 and Communist Party members in 1925.
The growing conservative influence in the Council was solidified when Dave Beck and his Teamsters came to dominate the group in the late 1920s. The third phase of the Council's history was thus business unionism, Beck-style. Dave Beck began his career as a driver for the Council's cooperative laundry but rapidly rose to become the chief Teamster organizer west of the Rockies. Beck used the strategic position of truck drivers in the economy to start rebuilding the strength of organized labor in Seattle. If the Council declared a firm to be "unfair to labor," he could often prevent the firm from trucking its goods to market. Despite Beck's occasionally ruthless tactics, he believed that businesses had a right to make a profit. When the Great Depression spurred widespread organizing drives, many firms concluded that they would much rather deal with the avowedly anti-radical Beck than with a CIO union. The Council routinely backed Beck in his jurisdictional disputes with CIO and independent unions. Thus, by the end of World War II, Seattle was largely a closed-shop AFL town. Under Beck's reign, the Council stayed fairly aloof from politics, endorsing moderate pro-labor Democrats and spurning the leftist coalitions that fought for local and state offices.
The fourth stage of the Council's history, its reentry into local politics, began with the merger of the AFL and CIO in 1955. The expanded Council was quickly put on the defensive by statewide right-to-work proposals in Initiative 198 in 1956 and Initiative 202 in 1958. The Council played a leading role in the campaigns that defeated these measures. After these victories, the Council went on the offensive. It started a pro-labor public relations campaign in 1959 that included donating money to charities and promoting radio and television appearances by labor leaders. Beginning in 1964, the Council's Committee on Political Education launched major voter registration drives before elections. The growth of public sector unions in the 1950s and 1960s, coupled with the addition of progressive CIO unions, led the Council to endorse expanded social services and public housing in this period. The Council also supported the efforts of Seattle civil rights groups during the 1960s. Nonetheless, the Council retained some traces of business unionism. It gave a no-strike pledge during the 1962 World's Fair and often helped the Chamber of Commerce lobby for subsidies for local businesses.
During the latter years of the 20th century, the period documented in Accession 1940-2, the council's executive secretaries were, in succession: James K. Bender, Dan Bickford, Ron Judd, and Steve Williamson.
In 2005, the name changed to Martin Luther King County Labor Council, commonly referred to as MLK Labor.
Organized into 6 accessions.
Accession No. 1940-001, King County Labor Council records, 1889-1970
Accession No. 1940-002, King County Labor Council records, 1970-2003
Accession No. 1940-003, King County Labor Council records, 1999-2008
Accession No. 1940-004, King County Labor Council. Provisional Trades Section minutes, 1935-1971
Accession No. 1940-005, Martin Luther King, Jr. County Labor Council records, 1965-2012
Accession No. 1940-006, Martin Luther King, Jr. County Labor Council records, 1984-2011
Correspondence, primarily with affiliated unions (1950-2011), minutes (1913-1970, 1987-1997, 1998-2012), financial records (1912-1919, 1982-1999), membership records (1889-1969), Delegate Roll Call Sign-In Ledgers (1965-1991), subject files (1925-2011), publications (1978-2011), banners from marches/events (1978-2011) and reports (1957-1959, 1966-1968). Also includes records of the Council's committees and affiliated labor organizations, including the Domestic Workers Union (1917), Seattle American Publishing Co. (1907), United Labor Advisory Committee Against Initiative 202 (1958), and United Labor Advisory Committee to Defeat Initiative 198 (1956), the Committee on Political Education (COPE) Records (2000-2005), and the Fight for 15 campaign (circa 2014).
Forms part of the Labor Archives of Washington.
The records are open to all users.
Issues of the Council's newspaper, The Scanner, that were received with the records were sent to the Microforms and Newspaper Collection, University of Washington Libraries.
Issues of Washington State Labor News, King County Labor News,Scanner/King County Labor News, and Labor's Voice, as well as Proceedings of the American Federation of Labor Convention that were received with accession 1904-005 were separated to be cataloged in Special Collections, University of Washington Libraries.
The Libraries' Microforms and Newspapers Collection owns a complete microfilm collection of the Union Record: The Official Journal of the Central Labor Council of Seattle and Vicinity and a partial microfilm run of The Scanner and King County Labor News. The Union Record was published from 1900 to 1928. The Scanner began in 1968 and is still printed.
Jonathan Dembo's An Historical Bibliography of Washington State Labor and Laboring Classes (unpublished, 1978) lists many published sources which deal with the history of the King County Central Labor Council. The most important recently published works which relate to the Council's history are Jonathan Dembo, Unions and Politics in Washington State (New York: Garland Publishing, 1983) and Dana Frank, Purchasing Power: Consumer Organizing, Gender, and the Seattle Labor Movement, 1919-1929 (New York: Cambridge University Press, 1994). There are essentially no books that deal with the post-1940 history of the Council.
AFL-CIO.$bKing County Labor Council$vArchives; AFL-CIO.$bMartin Luther King County Labor Council$vArchives; Western Central Labor Union (Seattle, Wash.)$vArchives; Central Labor Council of Seattle and Vicinity$vArchives; United Labor Advisory Committee to Defeat Initiative 198 (Wash.); United Labor Advisory Committee Against Initiative 202 (Wash.); Domestic Workers Union (Seattle, Wash.); Seattle American Publishing Co.; Labor Archives of Washington (University of Washington); Seattle (Wash.)$xPolitics and government; Washington (State)$xPolitics and government; Labor unions$zWashington (State)$vArchives; Labor unions$xPolitical activity; Domestics$xLabor unions$zWashington (State); Domestics$zWashington (State); Referendum$zWashington (State); Publishers and publishing$zWashington (State); Initiative 198 (Wash.); Initiative 202 (Wash.); Personal Papers/Corporate Records; Seattle; Washington (State); Labor History; Labor Unions; Photographs; Newsletters; Photographs; Clippings
- King County Labor Council records, 1889-1970; 1940-001; 18.26 cubic ft. 38 boxes
  Administrative Records primarily document the end of the third and the start of the fourth period of the Council's history. The bulk consists of the files of Chet W. Ramage, executive secretary of the Council from Oct. 1959 through 1968. Most correspondence dates from that period. There are virtually no letters from before 1950. Incoming letters are sorted and indexed by name of author, while outgoing and inter-office letters are organized chronologically. The correspondence primarily involved member unions and government officials. The subject files—which contain reports, memoranda, and some correspondence grouped together by subject—mostly cover topics between 1946 and 1970. There are, however, small subject files on the 1919 strike, the Council's internal power struggles in the early 1920s, and the AFL vs. CIO jurisdictional disputes of the 1930s. The accession also contains the complete minutes of the Council from 1915 to 1954 and from 1963 to 1970, documenting all of the organization's formal resolutions and actions. There is also a copy of the minutes of the Council's Executive Board for 1906 to 1907, 1913 to 1957, 1960 to 1965, and 1969 to 1970. The Executive Board's primary duty was to hear union complaints against local businesses and to decide which firms would be placed on the "unfair" list. In addition, the Council's membership and tax records from 1889 to 1962 are found in this accession.
  Records of the Council's committees make up another series. Included are committees to defeat the right-to-work initiatives in 1956 and 1958, the Public Relations Committee from 1959 to 1963, and the Committee on Political Education from 1963 to 1968 form another subgroup.
  The West Central Labor Union Records series consists of the minutes and the financial records of the Council's predecessor, the West Central Labor Union, from 1891 to 1905.
  The Other Labor Organizations series includes records from the United Labor Advisory Committee Against Initiative 202, the Seattle American Publishing Company, and others.
  View selections from this collection in digital format.
  Open to all users, but access to portions of the papers restricted. Contact repository for details.
  Donated by King County Labor Council in 1969 and 1972.
  - SERIES I: ADMINISTRATIVE RECORDS (Box-folder Boxes 1-24, 37, 38)
    - Subseries A: Historical Features, undated (Box-folder 1/1)
    - Subseries B: Organizational Features, 1961 (Box-folder 1/2)
    - Subseries C: Outgoing Letters, 1946-1968 (Box-folder 1/3-4)
    - Subseries D: General Correspondence
      - Adams, Brock, 1965-1968 (Box-folder 1/5)
      - Air Division - Rainier Lodge No. 3009, Brotherhood of Railway Clerks, 1961-1969 (Box-folder 1/6)
      - Air Line Pilots Association, 1960-1965 (Box-folder 1/7)
      - Alaska Fish Cannery Workers' Union of the Pacific, 1965 (Box-folder 1/8)
      - Allied Printing Trades Council, 1960, 1961, 1964, 1965 (Box-folder 1/9)
      - American Federation of Labor - President, 1950-1955 (Box-folder 1/10)
      - AFL-CIO. Organizers, 1959-1965 (Box-folder 1/11)
      - AFL-CIO. President (George Meany), 1957-1968 (Box-folder 1/12-13)
      - AFL-CIO. Maritime Trades Department, 1963, 1966-1967 (Box-folder 1/14)
      - AFL-CIO. Union Label and Service Trades Department, 1960, 1965-1969 (Box-folder 1/15)
      - AFL-CIO. Miscellaneous, 1957-1968 (Box-folder 1/16-17)
      - American Federation of Television and Radio Artists, 1960-1969 (Box-folder 1/18)
      - American Federation of Women's Auxiliary of Labor. Seattle Clerks Council, 1959 (Box-folder 1/19)
      - American Newspaper Guild, 1966 (Box-folder 1/20)
      - American Newspaper Guild #82, 1962, 1964, 1968 (Box-folder 1/21)
      - Arthritis and Rheumatism Foundation. Western Washington Chapter, 1960 (Box-folder 1/22)
      - Auto Painters, Local #518, 1960, 1968 (Box-folder 1/23)
      - Auto Sheet Metal Workers, Local #387, 1961, 1968 (Box-folder 1/24)
      - Automotive Machinists, International Association, Lodge # 289, 1958-1969 (Box-folder 2/1)
      - Automotive Trade Council of Seattle, King County and Vicinity, 1960-1965, 1967 (Box-folder 2/2)
      - Bakery and Confectionery Workers, Seattle Local, 1952 (Box-folder 2/3)
      - Barbers, Journeymen, International Union, Local #195, 1961-1969 (Box-folder 2/4)
      - Bartenders, International Union #487, 1962-1969 (Box-folder 2/5)
      - Beauticians, International Union, Local #195, 1960-1968 (Box-folder 2/6)
      - Bender, James, 1968 (Box-folder 2/7)
      - Bering Sea Fishermen's Union, 1968 (Box-folder 2/8)
      - Better Business Standards Association, 1960-1968 (Box-folder 2/9)
      - Bill Posters and Billers International Alliance, #49, 1961-1966 (Box-folder 2/10)
      - Boiler Makers, Iron Ship Builders, Helpers International Brotherhood, #104, 1960-1969 (Box-folder 2/11)
      - Bookbinders, International Brotherhood, Local #22, 1961-1962 (Box-folder 2/12)
      - Bookbinders, International Brotherhood, #87, 1960-1969 (Box-folder 2/13)
      - Boot and Shoe Workers Union, Local #37, 1960-1967 (Box-folder 2/14)
      - Re: Bostonian, Armene E. (National Labor Relations Board), 1964-1969 (Box-folder 2/15)
      - Boy Scouts of America, 1960, 1962, 1966 (Box-folder 2/16)
      - Brick and Clay Workers, United, Local #458, 1960, 1962 (Box-folder 2/17)
      - Brick and Clay Workers, United, Local #582, 1961-1969 (Box-folder 2/18)
      - Bricklayers, Masons, Plasterers, International Union, Local #2, 1967 (Box-folder 2/19)
      - Bridge, Structural and Ornamental Iron Workers International Association, Local #506, 1962-1969 (Box-folder 2/20)
      - Bridge, Structural, Reinforcing Steel and Ornamental Iron Workers, Riggers and Machinery Movers, Local #86, 1962-1969 (Box-folder 2/21)
      - Broom and Whisk Broom Makers, #84 (Lighthouse for the Blind), 1958-1961 (Box-folder 2/22-23)
      - Broom and Whisk Broom Makers, #84 (Lighthouse for the Blind), 1961-1963, 1966 (Box-folder 3/1)
      - Building and Construction Trades Council, Seattle, 1946, 1963-1969 (Box-folder 3/2-3)
      - Building Service Employees International Union, Local #6, 1958-1969 (Box-folder 3/4-7)
      - Building Trades Council, Seattle, 1946-1950 (Box-folder 3/8)
      - Card and Label League, Renton and Vicinity, 1966 (Box-folder 3/9)
      - Card and Label League, Seattle, 1953, 1968 (Box-folder 3/10)
      - Carpenters and Joiners, United Brotherhood, #131, 1962-1969 (Box-folder 3/11)
      - Carpenters and Joiners, United Brotherhood, Local #1368, 1964, 1965, 1969 (Box-folder 3/12)
      - Carpenters and Joiners, United Brotherhood, #1289, 1960-1969 (Box-folder 3/13)
      - Carpenters and Joiners, United Brotherhood, Local #1708, 1961 (Box-folder 3/14)
      - Carpenters and Joiners, United Brotherhood, Local #1797, 1958-1961, 1965 (Box-folder 3/15)
      - Carpenters and Joiners, United Brotherhood. Millmen's Union, Local #338, 1961-1969 (Box-folder 3/16)
      - Carpet, Linoleum, and Soft Tile Layers Union, Local #1238, 1964-1969 (Box-folder 3/17)
      - Cement, Lime, and Gypsum Workers', International Union #37, 1968 (Box-folder 3/18)
      - Cement, Lime, and Gypsum Workers', International Union #47, 1960-1969 (Box-folder 3/19)
      - Central Labor Councils, 1959-1966 (Box-folder 3/20)
        - Bremerton Labor Council
        - Grays Harbor Labor Council
        - Kitsap County Central Labor Council
        - Pierce County Central Labor Council
        - Skagit Valley Central Labor Council
        - Snohomish County Labor Council
        - Spokane County Labor Council
        - Wenatchee Central Labor Council
        - Whatcom County Central Labor Council
      - Central Labor Councils, East of the Mississippi, 1960, 1962, 1965 (Box-folder 3/21)
      - Central Labor Councils, West of the Mississippi, 1960-1968 (Box-folder 3/22)
      - Century Savings and Loan Association, 1961-1963 (Box-folder 3/23)
      - Re: Century 21 Meetings, 1958-1962 (Box-folder 4/1)
      - Chamber of Commerce, Seattle, 1964-1968 (Box-folder 4/2)
      - Chamber of Commerce, Seattle. Construction and Civic Development Division, 1961 (Box-folder 4/3)
      - Chemical Workers, International Union #121, 1960-1963, 1968 (Box-folder 4/4)
      - Children's Home Society, Washington, 1969 (Box-folder 4/5)
      - Citizens Committee for Postal Reform, 1969 (Box-folder 4/6)
      - Citizens Committee to Modernize 1909 Sunday Blue Law, 1961-1962 (Box-folder 4/7)
      - Committee of 100 - Continental, Inc. (Greater Seattle YMCA Development Program), 1961 (Box-folder 4/8)
      - Communications Workers of America, District 9, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 4/9)
      - Cooks and Assistants #33, 1960-1968 (Box-folder 4/10)
      - CIO Council, Seattle, 1957 (Box-folder 4/11)
      - Council of Planning Affiliates, 1968 (Box-folder 4/12)
      - Council on Aging, 1963-1968 (Box-folder 4/13)
      - Culinary Workers and Bartenders Union, Local #596, 1956, 1961, 1963, 1969 (Box-folder 4/14)
      - Democrats (Miscellaneous), 1963-1964, 1967 (Box-folder 4/15)
      - Dental Workers Union #29, 1961 (Box-folder 4/16)
      - Electrical, Radio, and Machine Workers International #1002, 1960-1969 (Box-folder 4/17)
      - Electrical, Radio, and Machine Workers International Union #1207, 1966-1969 (Box-folder 4/18)
      - Electrical Workers, International Brotherhood #46, 1959-1968 (Box-folder 4/19)
      - Electrical Workers, International Brotherhood #77, 1950, 1954, 1961-1969 (Box-folder 4/20)
      - Elevator Constructors, International Union #19, 1960-1968 (Box-folder 4/21)
      - Embalmers, Master Licensed #18189, 1960-1962 (Box-folder 4/22)
      - Farm Workers National Association (United Farm Workers), 1965-1969 (Box-folder 4/23)
      - Fire Fighters, International Association #27, 1961-1969 (Box-folder 4/24)
      - Fire Fighters, International Association, Local #864, 1969 (Box-folder 4/25)
      - Fire Fighters, International Association, (Renton) #1604, 1966 (Box-folder 4/26)
      - Fire Fighters, International Association #1257, 1961 (Box-folder 4/27)
      - Fire Fighters, International Association #1352, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 4/28)
      - Fire Fighters, International Association, (King County Fire District #11), Local #1810, 1969 (Box-folder 4/29)
      - Firemen and Oilers, International Brotherhood #193, 1961-1962, 1967-1968 (Box-folder 4/30)
      - Firemen's Marine Union. Seattle Branch, 1967 (Box-folder 4/31)
      - Flight Engineers International Association, Seattle, 1959-1962, 1966 (Box-folder 4/32)
      - Flint Glass Workers Union, American, Local #68, 1964-1965 (Box-folder 4/33)
      - Furniture Workers Union, Local #3197, 1960-1966 (Box-folder 4/34)
      - Garmatz, Edward, 1966 (Box-folder 4/35)
      - Garment Workers of America, United, Local #17, 1960-1969 (Box-folder 5/1)
      - Glass Bottle Blowers Association, Local #50, undated (Box-folder 5/2)
      - Glass Bottle Blowers Association, Local #87, 1962-1969 (Box-folder 5/3)
      - Glove Workers Union of America, undated (Box-folder 5/4)
      - Government Employees, American Federation, #40, 1960-1967 (Box-folder 5/5)
      - Government Employees, American Federation #2196, 1963 (Box-folder 5/6)
      - Grain Millers, American Federation, International #86, 1961-1969 (Box-folder 5/7)
      - Greater Seattle Incorporated, 1959-1969 (Box-folder 5/8)
      - Heat and Frost Inspectors and Asbestos Workers, International Association Local #7, 1965, 1969 (Box-folder 5/9)
      - Hod Carriers and General Laborers Union, Local #242, 1960-1969 (Box-folder 5/10)
      - Horseshoers Union, Local #13, 1961 (Box-folder 5/11)
      - Hospital Workers, Seattle and King County, Local #301, 1954-1960, 1964 (Box-folder 5/12)
      - Hotel and Restaurant Employees and Bartenders, International Union. Local Joint Executive Board, 1955-1968 (Box-folder 5/13-20)
      - Hotel, Motel, and Club Service Employees Union, Local #551, 1961-1969 (Box-folder 6/1)
      - Independence Day Celebration Committee, Seattle, 1960-1968 (Box-folder 6/2)
      - Inlandboatmen's Union of the Pacific, 1962-1969 (Box-folder 6/3)
      - Insurance Workers Union, International, Local #1, 1959, 1962-1965 (Box-folder 6/4)
      - International Little League Baseball Association, Seattle League, 1963 (Box-folder 6/5)
      - Jackson, Henry M., 1960-1968 (Box-folder 6/6)
      - Jewelry Workers Union, International, Local #30, 1961, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 6/7)
      - Journeymen Tailors Union, Local #71, 1961-1964, 1969 (Box-folder 6/8)
      - King County. Commissioners and Other County Offices, 1960-1967 (Box-folder 6/9)
      - King County Citizens For All-Purpose Stadium Now, 1966 (Box-folder 6/10)
      - King County Coroners Employees, Local #1652, 1960-1967 (Box-folder 6/11)
      - King County Law Enforcement Employees, Local #967, 1958-1963 (Box-folder 6/12)
      - King County Welfare Employees, Local #843, 1965-1969 (Box-folder 6/13)
      - KIRO Radio and Television, 1965-1966, 1969 (Box-folder 6/14)
      - Ladies Garment Workers Union, International, Local #184, 1960-1969 (Box-folder 6/15-16)
      - Laundry and Dry Cleaning Drivers, Local #566, 1964-1965 (Box-folder 6/17)
      - League of Women Voters of Seattle, 1960-1967 (Box-folder 6/18)
      - Leif Erikson League, 1964, 1968 (Box:oversize 37/1)
      - Letter Carriers, National Association, Seattle Branch, Local #79, 1960-1969 (Box-folder 6/19)
      - Litchman, Mark, 1963, 1965 (Box-folder 6/20)
      - Lithographers and Photoengravers, International Union #23, 1962-1966 (Box-folder 6/21)
      - Lithographers and Photoengravers, International Union, Local #45, 1964-1969 (Box-folder 6/22)
      - Luggage Workers Union, Local #51, 1959-1969 (Box-folder 6/23)
      - Lumber and Sawmill Workers' Union, Local #2519, 1959-1969 (Box-folder 6/24)
      - Machinists, International Association, Seattle Flight Engineer Lodge #1258, 1960-1964 (Box-folder 6/25)
      - Machinists, International Association, Hope Lodge #79, 1960-1969 (Box-folder 6/26)
      - Machinists, International Association, Aeronautical Industrial District, Lodge #751, 1959-1967 (Box-folder 6/27)
      - Machinists, International Association, Air Transport Lodge #1040, 1960-1961 (Box-folder 6/28)
      - Machinists, International Association, Air Transport Lodge #1351, 1964 (Box-folder 6/29)
      - Magnuson, Warren G., 1960-1968 (Box-folder 6/30)
      - Mailers Union, Seattle, Local #32, 1960-1969 (Box-folder 7/1)
      - Marine Cooks and Stewards, Seattle, 1958, 1960, 1964 (Box-folder 7/2)
      - Marine Engineers Beneficial Association, #38 and Pacific Coast District, 1959-1968 (Box-folder 7/3)
      - Maritime Trades Department, Puget Sound District Council, 1963-1969 (Box-folder 7/4)
      - Marking Device Union, Local #629, 1968 (Box-folder 7/5)
      - Masters, Mates and Pilots, International, Local #6, 1968 (Box-folder 7/6)
      - Meat Cutters and Butcher Workmen of North America, Amalgamated (Miscellaneous Locals), 1960, 1964, 1967 (Box-folder 7/7)
      - Meat Cutters and Butcher Workmen Union, Amalgamated, Meat Cutters, Local #81, 1961-1969 (Box-folder 7/8-9)
      - Meat Cutters and Butcher Workmen Union, Amalgamated, Packinghouse, Local #186, 1963-1964, 1968 (Box-folder 7/10)